Guide to the Elizabeth and Felix G. Rohatyn Papers Circa 1900?-2020 (bulk 1975-2012) MS 3015
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. General Correspondence and Subject Files, 1982-2016 (bulk, 2001-2010); 4.11 Linear feet
  - M. Miscellaneous (3 folders), 1995, 2001-2010 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19-21)
    Includes, among others, Danielle Mitterand, Congresswoman Carolyn B. Maloney, and Senator John McCain.
  - New York Rebuilding, 2000-2001 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
    Includes documents related to Rohatyn's articles concerning rebuilding in New York subsequent to the 9/11 attack on the World Trade Center. Among these are the New York City Comptroller's Office report The Impact of the September 11 WTC Attack on NYC's Economy and City Revenues (Preliminary Estimate) and documents concerning State Comptroller H. Carl McCall's consideration of using pension funds for reconstruction. See also the folders in this series on "Infrastructure" and "Pension Funds."
  - New York University, 2003 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
    Includes documents related to the the first NYU/NYSE Directors' Institute, at which Rohatyn was a panelist.
  - Nixon, Richard, 1989 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
    Includes one letter, responding favorably to Rohatyn's address at the Chicago Economic Club.
  - Nora, Pierre, 2002 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
    Includes documents, in French, concerning publication of an article by Rohatyn.
  - Notepad, circa 2012 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
    Includes a small notepad with to-do's, appointments and other daily notes.
  - Nuclear Threat Initiative (NTI)), 2005-2006 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
  - N. Miscellaneous, 1996, 2001-2005 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
  - O. Miscellaneous, 2001-2010 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29)
    Includes, among others, Supreme Court Justice Sandra Day O'Connor and a copy of Rohatyn's letter to President Barack Obama supporting Hugh Carey as a recipient for the Presidential Medal of Freedom.
  - Pension Funds (2 folders), 2001-2002 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 30-31)
    Includes documents related to a meeting of state investment officials convened by Rohatyn, California State Treasurer Philip Angelides and New York Comptroller H. Carl McCall; see also the folders in this series on "Infrastructure" and "New York Rebuilding."
  - Pharmaceutical Companies, 2002, 2010 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 32)
    Includes Board of Director meeting packages for Aton Pharma (2002) and ARMGO (2010).
  - Powell, Colin, 2001 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
  - Protectionism & Foreign Capital Movements, 2006 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    Includes draft of an article by Rohatyn on this subject for the Council on Foreign Relations.
  - Publicis Groupe Supervisory Board, 2010 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
  - P. Miscellaneous (2 folders), 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4-5)
    Includes, among others, Congresswoman Nancy Pelosi.
  - "Rebuilding New York City: The Federal Role" Forum. Sponsored by the Association of the Bar of the City of New York's Committee on Federal Legislation (2 folders), 2002 December 16 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6-7)
    Includes the background material for the forum.
  - Rendell, Edward, 2008-2010 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
    Includes various documents concerning infrastructure, including a draft of Rohatyn's comments to the National Governor's Association (2009), the results of a "Building America's Future" survey taken by Frank Luntz (2009), a white paper by a task force of the American Bar Association on the federal budget in relation to infrastructure (2008); and comments by Rohatyn to Governor Rendell on a national infrastructure bank (2010).
  - Rohatyn Associates LLC (3 folders), 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9-11)
    Includes an announcement of the firm's organization (2001), financial statements for various periods (2001-2002), editions of the supervisory procedures and compliance manual (2001-2006), and other required firm policy and procedure statements (2006).
  - R. Miscellaneous (3 folders), 1995, 2001-2010 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12-14)
    Includes, among others, Congressman Charles B. Rangel, Senator John D. Rockefeller IV and Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld.
  - Sarkozy, Nicolas, 2002-2007 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
  - SBC Communications. Project Universe, 2002 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16)
    Includes presentation with overview and analysis of U.S. telecommunications industry and companies.
  - FGR's Signature (Photocopies), Undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
  - Strategic Council for Attractiveness, 2003-2004 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18)
    Includes documents related to the French advisory council on the economy and industry, of which Rohatyn was a member.
  - Student Immigration, 2004-2006 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 19)
    Includes Rohatyn's remarks at the inauguration of Dr. Clara Yu at the Monterey Institute of International Studies, and related documents.
  - S. Miscellaneous (6 folders), 2001-2010, 2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 20-25)
    Includes, among others, Secretary of the Treasury John W. Snow, Senator Gordon H. Smith, Senator Debbie Stabenow, and former German Chancellor Helmut Schmidt.
  - Transition, Governor-elect Eliot Spitzer. Economic Development Advisory Committee (5 folders), 2006 November-December (Offsite-box 3, Folder 26-30)
  - Trinity School, New York. Annual Report, 2009 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 31)
  - T. Miscellaneous, 2000-2010 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - U.N. Secretary General / AIDS, 2001 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
  - United Way of New York City. Knickerbocker Circle. Information Packet, Circa 2001 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
  - U.S. Conference of Mayors, 2001-2003 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
  - U. Miscellaneous, 2002-2009 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
    Includes Rohatyn's testimony, forwarded to Louis Uchitelle of the New York Times, concerning the role of public investment in promoting economic growth delivered before the U.S. House of Representatives Committee on Financial Services (2007).
  - V. Miscellaneous, 2001-2010 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
    Includes, among others, Paul Volcker's positive response to Rohatyn's remarks on "Freedom, Fairness and American Capitalism," with Volcker's dinner speech at the SIEPR Economic Summit (2005).
  - W. Miscellaneous, 1995, 2000-2011 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
  - 92nd Street Y, 2002-2003 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
    Includes remarks and related documents.
  - Y, Z. Miscellaneous, 2001-2005 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
  - General Reference & News Articles (7 folders), 1970s-2016 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10-16)
    Includes miscellaneous newspaper articles, magazines, Internet publications, and other print matter concerning economics, business, infrastructure spending, culture, and Lazard, some with highlighting. Several articles refer to Rohatyn, or even emphasize him specifically. None include articles written by Rohatyn or include interviews where he is quoted extensively; see the above folders and, especially, Series III for those. See Series II for press clips concerning the 1970s New York City fiscal crisis.
- Series II. New York City Fiscal Crisis, 1975-2013; 0.25 Linear feet
  The series includes a few documents concerning New York's fiscal crisis of the mid-late 1970s. These include 21 rolls of 35mm photographic negatives relating to the Municipal Assistance Corporation (MAC) taken in August 1978 by Carl Roodman. The most recognizable subject matter is the 8 August 1978 visit to City Hall by President Jimmy Carter where he signed legislation giving a $1.65 billion Federal loan guarantee to the city. There are photographs of the crowds, speakers at the podium, Carter's arrival and bill signing, and other such shots of the event. The specific subject matter of the other photographs is somewhat uncertain as to what is being depicted. But these appear to be photographs of the MAC staff at work in their offices in 2 World Trade Center; meetings and working sessions among various principals; discussions between MAC Executive Director Eugene Keilin, Rohatyn, and others; and possibly of the MAC Special Board Meeting of 11 August 1978, which took place at the midtown law office of Paul, Weiss, Rifkind.
  In addition to the photographs, there are photocopies of press clippings, the issue of Newsweek featuring Rohatyn on its cover, a transcript of a US Senate hearing at which Rohatyn spoke, and articles, mostly from the 2000s, that included reflections on the events of the mid-1970s.
  The series is arranged roughly by format and in chronological order.
  Related Archival Materials Note
  The records of the Municipal Assistance Corporation for the City of New York (MAC) are held by the Newman Library at Baruch College. The on-line finding aid is at http://www.baruch.cuny.edu/library/alumni/online_exhibits/amfl/mac/mac_finding_aid_index.htm
  - Press Clips (Binder Content) (2 folders), 1975-1979 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 17-18)
  - Transcript. US Senate Committee on Banking, Housing and Urban Affairs. Hearings on New York City Financial Aid Legislation, 1978 June 7 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 19)
  - Municipal Assistance Corporation (MAC). 35mm Photographs (negatives), 1978 August (Offsite-box 4, Folder 20)
    Roll 17 and 18 include photographs of President Jimmy Carter at City Hall. Rolls 2, 5, and 19 might depict scenes from the MAC Special Board meeting of 11 August.
  - Newsweek's "The Cities' Mr. Fixit" Issue, 1981 May 4 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 21)
  - Later Reflections, 1984, 2003, 2012-2013 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 22)
    Includes a chapter from Jewel and Bernard Bellush's book Union Power and New York (1984), Rohatyn's speech at Columbia University "New York Fiscal Crises: 1975-2003" (2003), the article "New York City in 1975" in CRC Notes (2012), a letter to the editor of The Economist (2013), and an opinion piece by Rohatyn and Peter Goldmark in Newsday (2013).
- Series III. Remarks, Speeches and Writings, 1980s-2016; 2.8 Linear feet
  The series includes the texts of various prepared speeches, testimony or other public remarks Rohatyn delivered, primarily from 2001 to 2009, with a few from earlier and later years. (Speeches made during his years as ambassador to France are found in Series IV.) The subjects of these remarks centered on the role of government in spending on infrastructure, economic relationships between the U.S. and Europe, capitalism, recollections of New York City's fiscal crisis, and other matters concerning political economy. Audiences included houses of the U.S. Congress, the 92nd Street Y, New York Public Library, the Institute of French Studies at New York University, City University of New York (CUNY), the U.S. Conference of Mayors, AFSCME, the Chicago Humanities Festival, the World Affairs Council, the Academie des Sciences Morales et Politiques, COFACE, the Kennedy School of Government at Harvard, the Center for American Progress, the Economic Club of Chicago, the American Library in Paris, the National Governors Association, and others. Some of these texts are in French.
  The series also includes Rohatyn's writings on mostly economic policy subjects. These take the form of clippings, photocopies and tear sheets from newspapers and other periodicals in which opinion pieces authored or co-authored by Rohatyn appeared. These also date primarily from 2000 to 2008. (Articles and clippings that refer to Rohatyn or quote him in passing are generally not found in this series, but are in the general reference files of Series I. Articles concerning New York's fiscal crisis are in Series II.)
  The series includes extensive, various drafts of Rohatyn's memoirs, which were published under the title Dealings, but were also known by a working title of Money Games. These range from early drafts of chapters written in 2002 to the final versions published in 2010. There are also some drafts of Rohatyn's book on the history of major capital investments by the U.S. government, Bold Endeavors (working title: Investing in America), and portions of the French version of the book.
  The series also includes published interviews of Rohatyn and profile articles centering on particular aspects of Rohatyn's career and perspective. There are copies of a videotape of a televised 2000 interview of Rohatyn by Charlie Rose. (The tape is restricted from use because the library lacks playback equipment, but the interview can be viewed, with a transcript, at the Charlie Rose show website: https://charlierose.com/videos/16773. That site also includes videos of several other appearances on the Charlie Rose Show that are not in this collection.)
  The series is arranged with remarks/speeches first, followed by Rohatyn's writings and interviews.
  - Remarks (1 of 7 folders), 1992, 1999-2001 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
  - Remarks (2 of 7 folders), 2002 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
  - Remarks (3 of 7 folders), 2003 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
  - Remarks (4 of 7 folders), 2004-2005 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
  - Remarks (5 of 7 folders), 2006-2008 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
  - Remarks (6 of 7 folders), 2009 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
  - Remarks (7 of 7 folders), 2010-2012, Undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
  - Opinion Pieces (1 of 3), 1987, 1996, 2001-2007 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8)
  - Opinion Pieces (2 of 3), 2008-2014 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
  - Opinion Pieces (3 of 3). Flat File, 2002, 2008 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 1)
    Includes two issues of the New York Review of Books with articles by Rohatyn.
  - Interviews & Features (1 of 3 folders), 1980s, 2000-2003 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
  - Interviews & Features (2 of 3 folders), 2006-2013 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 11)
  - Interviews & Features (3 of 3 folders). Flat File, 1984 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 7)
    Includes the New York Times Magazine of 5 August 1984, with its cover article "Life at the Top: The Power and Pleasures of Financier Felix Rohatyn."
  - Interview with Charlie Rose (Videotape, 4 copies), 2000 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 12)
    The videotape is restricted from use because N-YHS does not have playback equipment in the Library. See the on-line version at https://charlierose.com/videos/16773.
  - Interviews on DVDs, 2007, 2009 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 13)
    Includes 3 DVDs: Rohatyn interviewed by Dall Forsythe at Baruch College (10 July 2007); Rohatyn on Reuters Financial TV (7 April 2009); and a Rohatyn interview dated 21 October 2009.
  - The Twenty-Year Century: Essays on Economics and Public Finance, 1983 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 14)
    Includes a photocopy of Rohatyn's book of essays.
  - Dealings. Drafts (7 of 26 folders), 2002-2010 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 15-21)
  - Dealings. Drafts (12 of 26 folders), 2002-2010 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-12)
  - Dealings. Drafts, Images and Notes (7 of 26 folders), 2003-2010 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-6)
  - Dealings. Congratulatory Letters, Promotional Events, Reviews (2 folders), 2010-2011 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 7-8)
  - Bold Endeavors / Investing in America. Drafts and Notes (4 folders), 2006-2008 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9-12)
  - Bold Endeavors. French Version (Ces Hommes Qui Ont Fait l'Amerique) (2 folders), 2010 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 13-14)
- Series IV. Ambassadorship Files, 1994-2001 (bulk, 1997-2000); 2.2 Linear feet
  The series includes files related to Felix Rohatyn's tenure as U.S. Ambassador to France (1997-2000). These include speeches, remarks, interviews, and written articles by Rohatyn, which generally concerned economic matters, relations between the U.S. and France, and Europe generally, and globalization. Also included are many of Rohatyn's daily schedules; his letter of instruction from President Bill Clinton; documentation concerning the American Presence Posts (APP) initiative, which established small Foreign Service posts in five key cities around France in support of American businesses and citizens; color slides of the paintings in the ambassador's residence; documents related to Rohatyn's confirmation and presentation of credentials; and his resignation and farewell. The series also includes Elizabeth Rohatyn's schedules and lunch and dinner events, providing insight into the role played by the ambassador's spouse in the social protocols of diplomacy. Many of the documents are in French.
  The series is arranged by subject, in roughly chronological order: confirmation documents are first, followed by speeches, schedules, and other files related to Rohatyn's ambassadorship, and closing with resignation documents and farewell letters.
  - Confirmation Documents (2 folders), 1997 July (Offsite-box 7, Folder 15-16)
  - Statements at Confirmation Hearing & at Swearing-in Ceremony, 1997 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 17)
  - Credentials & Protocols, 1997 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 18)
  - Speeches and Remarks. Index to Books, 1994-2000 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1)
  - Speeches and Remarks. Distribution Lists, 1997-1999 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 2)
  - Speeches. Book 1 (2 folders), 1994-1998 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3-4)
    Includes two statements from 1994 and 1995 (prior to Rohatyn's tenure as ambassador), both concerning economic globalization.
  - Speeches. Book 2 (2 folders), 1998-1999 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 5-6)
  - Speeches. Book 3 (2 folders), 1999 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 7-8)
  - Speeches. Book 4 (2 folders), 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 9-10)
  - Speeches. Book 5 (2 folders), 2000 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 11-12)
  - Speeches. Additional Copies, 1994-2000 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 13)
  - Speech. Elizabeth Rohatyn at Cercle de l'Union Interalliee, 2000 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 14)
    The speech is in French, though there is a draft in English. Includes biographical reflections, particularly in connection with her Board and philanthropic activities and her role as the wife of the U.S. ambassador to France.
  - Remarks. Book 1 (2 folders), 1997-1998 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 15-16)
  - Remarks. Book 2 (2 folders), 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 17a-b)
  - Remarks. Additional Copies, 1997-1998 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 18)
  - Interviews, 1998-1999 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 19)
  - Articles, 1996-2000 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 20)
  - Clippings & Magazines (7 folders), 1997-2001 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 21-27)
  - American Presence Posts (APP), 1998-2000 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 28)
  - American Presence Posts. American Academy of Diplomacy Agenda, 2000 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 29)
  - Patrick Seignolle Realisation Pelco (PSR). Ambassade des Etas Unit, Reperage du 27 03 1998 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 30)
    Includes photos concerning work to be done on the embassy building.
  - President Bill Clinton Letter. Instructions to Ambassador Rohatyn, 1997 August 1 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
  - Inspector's Evaluation Report, 1998 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 2)
  - Cemetery Information. Conde sur Vesgre, 2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 3)
  - Embassy Housekeeping Job Descriptions, circa 1997 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 4)
  - Color Slides of Residence Paintings, 1997-2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5)
  - Madeleine Albright / Yasser Arafat Political Cartoon. Flat File, 2000 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 5)
    Includes a cartoon by Bill Garner of the Washington Times, with a note to Felix and Elizabeth Rohatyn from Madeleine Albright, referring to a diplomatic incident with the Palestinian leader on 4 October 2000.
  - Rohatyn Birthday Party, 1998 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6)
    Includes invitations, entrance card, etc. for Rohatyn and his son's birthday party, held in Paris, with a Humphrey Bogart/Casablanca theme. Includes a cartoon flip book of Rohatyn as the smoking Bogart character.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1998, 2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 7)
  - Blank Stationery, circa 2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 8)
  - Blue Cards / Ambassador's Schedule, 1998 September-December (Offsite-box 9, Folder 9)
  - Blue Cards / Ambassador's Schedule (2 folders), 1999 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 10a-b)
  - Blue Cards / Ambassador's Schedule (2 folders), 2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 11a-b)
  - Elizabeth Rohatyn Schedules, 1998-2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 12)
  - Dinners-In (3 folders), 1997-2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 13-15)
  - Dinners-Out (2 folders), 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 16-17)
  - Ladies' Luncheon-In, 1998-2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 18)
  - Luncheons-Out, 2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence Received From U.S. Correspondents (3 folders), 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 20-22)
    Principally includes letters and notes to Elizabeth Rohatyn. Correspondents include Madeleine Albright, Alan Greenspan, Richard Avedon, and Supreme Court Justice Stephen Breyer.
  - Correspondence Received From France Correspondents (2 folders), 2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 23-24)
  - Correspondence Sent Out. Thank You Letters, 1998-2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 25)
  - Access Cards, 1998-2001 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 26)
    Includes passes to the Louvre, L'Association des Amis du Musee Gustave Moreau, Musee d'Orsay, Centre Pompidou, and ICOM membership card.
  - Biographical Introductions, 1997-1998 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 27)
  - Resignation Letters, 2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 28)
    Includes a letter from President Bill Clinton acknowledging Rohatyn's letter of resignation and Secretary of State Madeleine Albright's letter at the conclusion of Rohatyn's tenure as Ambassador.
  - Farewell Reception (3 folders), 2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 29-31)
  - Goodbye Letters (2 folders), 2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 32-33)
    Includes letters from Consul General Samuel V. Brock, President Jacques Chirac and the ambassadors to France from various other countries.
  - Goodbye Letters. Marc Riboud, 2001 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 34)
    Includes a letter and inscribed photograph to the Rohatyns from Riboud.
- Series V. Elizabeth Rohatyn Board Files, 1993-2013; 3 Linear feet
  The series includes Elizabeth Rohatyn's files concerning her work on the boards of three organizations: French Regional & American Museum Exchange (FRAME), Teaching Matters Inc. (TMI), and the New York Public Library (NYPL). The material concerning FRAME is perhaps the richest as it includes documentation related to the founding, first decade, activities, and evolution of this international cultural organization's operations from 1999 forward. The TMI files also include concept papers, Board minutes, program proposals, and other materials concerning the organization's mission and development, but coverage is inconsistent, dating mostly from the 2000s, well after the organization's founding in 1994. Similarly, the New York Public Library files include useful Board and Committee level documents spanning 2002 to 2013, but there is a high level of inconsistency in coverage from year to year.
  The series is organized in three subseries:
  Subseries V.A. French Regional & American Museum Exchange (FRAME)
  Subseries V.B. Teaching Matters Inc. (TMI)
  Subseries V.C. New York Public Library (NYPL)
  - Subseries V.A. French Regional & American Museum Exchange (FRAME), 1999-2012; 1.33 Linear feet
    Biographical/Historical Note
    The French Regional & American Museum Exchange (FRAME), now known by the somewhat abbreviated name of French American Museum Exchange, was founded in 1999 by Elizabeth Rohatyn during her husband's, Felix Rohatyn's, tenure as U.S. ambassador to France. The mission of the organization was, and is, to develop U.S.-France cultural exchanges in the context of museum collaborations for exhibitions, education programs, and the like. Elizabeth served as one of FRAME's two Founding Co-Presidents, the other being Francoise Cachin, who was then the Director of the Musées de France. FRAME's Founding Director was art historian Dr. Richard Brettell of the University of Texas.